[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is the Avijja Sutta, Sutta on Ignorance, Anguttara 1061.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it is said that no first point of ignorance is evident, before which there was no ignorance, and afterwards ignorance came to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as you said, quite a lot, ignorance is beginningless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ignorance of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can answer in many different ways, but the point is, practically speaking, you don't start in a neutral position.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already start, begin, hindered, obstructed, obsessed, limited, restricted,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what ignorance is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do you... why is it that...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, yeah, obviously, it's because that's how it is, but why is it so sort of difficult to not see the possibility of not ignoring?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because you have no reference point that's not affected by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any standpoint you take, partakes in ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's rooted in ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's so difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no standpoint can just suddenly show you a situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are no markers for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any standpoint you take, will be ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, top to bottom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you then figure your way out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's where the gradual training comes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: You figure it out by upholding certain behaviors, sense restraint, virtue, which in return diminishes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that you can see it, not at a time.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see it later on, after which your efforts would have been verified, but initially you can't see.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can make some sense, you know, out of it, if you're authentic and intelligent and so on, but fundamentally it comes down to doing it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Regardless of your standpoints, keeping the precepts, guarding the sense doors, watching your intentions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that diminishes that vicious... weakens that vicious cycle of ignorance feeding more ignorance, standpoints feeding more standpoints.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you stick to those training precepts, and tame your mind within that, then you get to see your situation from the inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's sotāpati, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what we said in that... the seven... the relay chariot sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the views will be purified, not because you figured it all out intellectually and made sense out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The views are purified when your behavior is purified, when the composure is regained within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, samādhi results... direct result from nothing else other than sensory strength and precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Purification of the views is a result of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not natural.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not something that one would...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, yeah, what is natural is to want pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, the most natural thing is to put your standpoints first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The craving for the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the views are the most blameworthy thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wrong view is the most blameworthy thing, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you would go against that grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Against that tendency.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not that you can stop having views, but you can certainly stop emphasizing them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, put your views aside, review your behavior, your actions, and purify it like... like a skilled goldsmith would be purifying gold.
[SPEAKER_00]: First from coarse impurities, then more refined impurities, then more refined impurities.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, next thing you know, you don't have those standpoints anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can see what proceeds at the standpoint.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you just don't have them anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're gone, because they have been unplugged.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you've seen the context, or you've been able to... No, because you purified them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You purified them through sense restraint, watchfulness of your intentions, general taming of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then these views have lost their power, their weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: The standpoints, yeah, the wrong emphasis is disappeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can have, still, thoughts and standpoints, but they won't be carrying the same weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: They won't be emphasized, because now you know exactly how the mind is stained, how the views are diminished, and how the freedom from suffering is developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through gradual training, not through the opinions on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the opinions that persist would then just be, without that weight, would be a correct representation of what you did.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, an arahant cannot ignore... No, no, no, because arahant's mind cannot be untamed anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot be provoked anymore, cannot be disturbed, cannot be perturbed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, no views, no standpoints can arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this sutta gives ten fuels for the... for ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: For ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to clarify before going there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ignorance is not on the level of the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not on the level of, oh, I haven't read enough suttas to figure things out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of that self-induced delusion, distraction, greed, aversion through your acts and your choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what ignorance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Choosing to turn a blind eye.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's basically what the Sutta says, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, it is evident that there is a specific condition for ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: I say that ignorance is fueled by the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_02]: As you say, yeah, it's acting out of
[SPEAKER_00]: Acting out of pressures, obsessions, I mean, the five hindrances, they all boil down to greed, aversion, distraction, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, choosing to act out of those things, you're fueling a vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're fueling the attitude of ignoring, turning a blind eye, of not being clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the translation of moha is delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delusion, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Moha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds... sounds like delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like moha.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're a fool, kind of.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I like the the translation of distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's a practical thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know when you're distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's some recognition there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, I guess, so most person who's ignorant, he's distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he's ignorant because he keeps himself distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, he doesn't know that he's necessarily distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's engaged with the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, an intoxicated person is not aware of his... that he's drunk.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was just going to... Until he sobers up.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was just going to bring up the intoxication, like, even the way that the Buddha talks about, like, the intoxication of youth, the intoxication of life.
[SPEAKER_03]: And health.
[SPEAKER_03]: And health, in the sense that, like, old age, sickness and death are not things that are hidden.
[SPEAKER_03]: From people, things that are... they're very obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nor are the things that will come later.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're already here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're already subjected... subject to the possibility of people all around you can fall... fall sick, die, get old, and so you... you could pay more heed to them, but it's like this... yeah, that feeling... intoxicates it.
[SPEAKER_00]: An intoxication
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot exist on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you would sober up if you stop drinking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fact that you're not sobering up means because you're still consuming alcohol.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this sense, the fact that you're not sobering up from these intoxications is because you're still consuming things that keep you intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual desire, acting out of aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like a similar principle of
[SPEAKER_03]: Trying, basically, forgetfulness, almost, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Deliberately induced forgetfulness of the things that are obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it's like a coping habit.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's funny, because you only need to try and forget that thing, if it's already kind of, on some level, recognized that it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, you wouldn't need to
[SPEAKER_01]: But the forgetfulness is a pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even though you know what you're forgetting about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just that, you know, shutting your eyes, covering your head is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if... that's the funny thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if you...
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if you are, say, even in terms of intoxication, like, if you're in a situation where you know it's really, you know, you must not forget, you must not become just careless or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know, you're driving or something or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: Most people, at least, if you have some degree of
[SPEAKER_03]: of carefulness or whatever, you wouldn't, you wouldn't, you know, if you might, I don't know, drink a small amount of alcohol or something, but if you were to realize, oh, I'm actually, I'm starting to become intoxicated, it would be
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not seen as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_03]: It would be seen as, okay, I can't let myself forget this, because I need, because I can see the danger of forgetting.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, in other words, you can only, you know, take pleasure in forgetting if you're already intoxicated to some degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and that's that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already start as being intoxicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no reference point of sobriety.
[SPEAKER_02]: The neutral position is seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's how you work towards the neutral position.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yes, you could still technically become careless, but then the danger is much more apparent in doing so.
[SPEAKER_00]: As opposed to somebody who is in the beginning, when there's like no reference point for the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, like, that's why, you know, I know when I started reading the suttas, you know, back as a layman and
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, you know, you have all these views and so on, but I remember, like, you read the suttas and it just seemed almost as if a matter of a fact that monks would just get the right view upon going into seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there is the Buddha, then they go and dwell diligent and withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there was kind of not quite fitting with the assumption that the right view is on the level of figuring out things and having this magical kind of breakthrough insight type into stuff that just suddenly surprised you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was like, what are they diligent about?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are they withdrawn from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where do you like... Oh!
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody makes the effort, right view was the necessary result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody makes that right effort,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, just, he comes, he talks to the Buddha, the Buddha instructs him, he goes, and he dwells resolute and diligent, and then, in no time, and then another one, and then another one, and then another one, and then you may think, oh, well, because, you know, they were lucky, talking to the Buddha and so on, but no.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were the ones, diligent and resolute.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, diligent and resolute about what?
[SPEAKER_00]: About spinning their mind constantly around how to figure this out, how to figure this out, rehashing everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, maybe some, to some extent, but there is probably some more kind of practical unifying thread, that all these different monks, regardless, you know, one might have arrived through faith, another might have arrived through discernment and reasoning, another one might have arrived through composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, they all simply partake in diligence and resoluteness of keeping the mind away from unwholesome states, and they all arrive at the right view and arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you realize, aha, because that's where the emphasis is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not on a magical breakthrough through sensation experience of a meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not certainly through scholastic figuring out, you know, the implicit meaning, the hidden meanings of the Pali terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's also not on the level of account... on the kind of just mere reasoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can reason all you want, but as I said many times before,
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind is not tamed through the gradual training in the right order,
[SPEAKER_00]: Obedrawal and diligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, diligence not, I'm diligent, I'm gonna walk 20 kilometers and carry 50 liters of water on my back and live on top of a mountain and I'm diligent, I'm diligent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, that's one way of being diligent, but that's not the diligence we talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Diligence that matters is diligence of recognizing the unwholesome intention whenever it arises on a day-to-day basis and simply not acting out of it, enduring it without losing context in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every single time, no exception.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's literally the all that you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, whether you reason, whether you ponder, whether you speculate, that will all sort of fall into place.
[SPEAKER_02]: I say that the five hindrances are fueled by
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why can't I stop acting out?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm sure everybody at some point has asked himself that question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here is why.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're not restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not restrained enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still, willingly, consciously, in full volition, choosing non-sense restraint, when those options present themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, maybe not as bad as you used to be or something, but factually, if you still can't help but act out, it's because you still have not purified the restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: The relay chariots.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing one's responsibility here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing that the direct reason for you still acting out is your choices made on a day-to-day basis that contradict the sensory strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're still fueling it and then it burns.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be surprised all you want, but you are the one pouring the fuel.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I say that the lack of sense-restraint is fueled by a lack of mindfulness and situational awareness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you're saying, this contradiction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you're acting out of...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you lose sense-restraint, because you lost the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how'd you lose the context, then?
[SPEAKER_00]: How'd you lose mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that happened accidentally, just like, you blink and it's gone?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, again, by choosing to repeatedly attend, intend, engage with,
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that you know eventually lead to unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they might not be bad at its face value right there, obviously bad, but you know like, yeah, but this will lead to what it led so many times before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you ignore that hint, you ignore that sign, that cue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not guarding the sense doors, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when it comes to breaking the sense restraint, it's like the most natural decision at the time, because the mind is already inclined in that direction way before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, you can't stop that momentum.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas, if one practices sense restraint, then the possibility of seeing, yeah, this context of the already arisen nature of experience proceeding, yeah, my self or, yeah, that is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, that remains, yeah, that remains unobstructed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always there, but the possibility of seeing it is...
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing, like, while the views are still emphasized, a person might be making loads of effort, like, tremendous amount of effort to keep clarifying that, keep clarifying what's already there, what isn't before me, not mine, but not actually purifying the sense restraint, withdrawal and not acting out of intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're still... your effort's wasted, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your emphasis is in the end, not the beginning of it, of that development.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first try.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, sure, bring back that, oh, I remind myself of the context, but then also continue and ask yourself, why did you lose the context in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you need to keep reminding yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you need to keep rehashing things that you understood?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are they still liable to doubt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you bothered by it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well, because the taming that precedes it has not been developed, not sufficiently developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, of course, it's not going to be perfect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you're suddenly going to stop everything else and you do one, two, three.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, technically, theoretically possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind will still be jumping at the end, in the beginning, the middle and so on, but as long as you now know what comes first is first, you will not get, like, too carried away, say, in spinning, you know, doubt and trying to figure it out,
[SPEAKER_00]: While you know that, well, this is the result, this is the symptom of an underlying problem of insufficient, enduring things on the right level, insufficient restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say insufficient restraint, it does not mean, okay, so now I will really restrain myself, I will lock myself in a little box, I won't move, I will barely breathe, I will not do anything, because that's not sense restraint, that's now self-torture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense-restraint is when you are moving around freely throughout your day and then you have an intention that's directed towards sense-desire, aversion, distraction on the level of the body, speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's which you don't act.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you say that you
[SPEAKER_01]: Know that that's what you're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know enough of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since, you know, indulgence is wrong, it's going to block my progress, everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: I keep precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the pressure comes to break those precepts, or break restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all the knowledge you have,
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's too distant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very nice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's deep and meaningful, whatever, but it's too far away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you break your restraint, to whatever degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you... ah, okay, ah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you suffer on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you try again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: To build up the restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Build up the restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And listen, you know, hear the same discussion on sense-restraint again and again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the pressure builds up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once again, you... With all that knowledge, you break that sense-restraint.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, so what...
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's to say, that's a person who is just alone, doing the practice themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's... you can get stuck in a loop by yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you got all the information about the dangers of sensual indulgence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to keep sensual strength, yet you yourself are breaking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then trying again and breaking it, so you just insulate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, when it comes to that, when your inspiration and things you know kind of drifts away into distance, and now pressure to break sensory strain is there, and you act out of it, well, see, the point is that that pressure to break the sensory strain does not just magically appear out of nowhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does not... does not come overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were just like one moment, you were... you were really like full-on established in the right context, everything is clear, and the next moment it's... oh, you're about to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, all of it is gone, suddenly, hundred miles away.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means there have been things in between that that person was careless about, that that person was negligent, distract himself with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was accumulating.
[SPEAKER_01]: A kind of gradual training in the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so it was exactly, yeah, yeah, of course, whatever mind frequently thinks and ponders, that's what it will incline towards, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might not be thinking core stuff, but there is stuff on the level of distraction, indolence, oblivion, and so on, that you are repeatedly, repeatedly engaging, even in solitude and so on, and then the pressure is building up, and the clarity is drifting away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I said before, like, it's recognizing the little things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, you know, the Buddha said it himself, like the skillful cook and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, before these states of mind come and pressure you, where you kind of know you're going to lose sense restraint to a degree, you start learning and foreseeing, like, the little telltales.
[SPEAKER_01]: Danger is in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is not a fault, technically.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, every single time in the past, when I went and was engaging with things of this nature, here and there, I did have sensual arise later on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unrelated to this directly, but still related to the acts around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's when you build it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that kind of... that pressure that has been accumulated and now it's making you act.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't come out of nowhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you might seem that way, because for the same reason as we said when we started this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're still emphasizing the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to understand that what you're going through is still the result of other actions that you've been ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes you can feel like, but look, I'm doing everything right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now there is this pressure here.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in the sutta, there's an analogy which is like, yeah, perfect for describing what you just said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it says, it's like when the rain pours down on a mountaintop, and the water flows downhill to fill the hollows, the crevices, and the creeks.
[SPEAKER_02]: As they become full, they fill up the pools.
[SPEAKER_02]: The pools fill up the lakes.
[SPEAKER_02]: The lakes fill up the streams.
[SPEAKER_02]: It accumulates.
[SPEAKER_02]: The streams fill up the rivers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Spills over.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as the rivers become full, they fill up the ocean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the fuel for the ocean.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how it is filled up.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same way, when the factor of associating with...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, these are the factors we didn't come to yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: When the factor of associating with bad people is fulfilled, it fulfills the factor of listening to an untrue teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: When the factor of listening to an untrue teaching is fulfilled, it fulfills the factor of a lack of faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then... And that's exactly what I've been describing.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, like, it doesn't mean untrue teachings from some ridiculously, like, wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, means simply the wrong instructions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instructions not clear enough, not emphasizing the right things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will lack faith, means basically you will lack ability to emphasize that which doesn't seem
[SPEAKER_00]: Natural to emphasize.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't seem the most important or pressing thing to emphasize.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't emphasize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll emphasize what you think you should emphasize.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you start hearing the... so somebody... you come across the teaching that's actually rightly expounded and tells you, well, you should stop emphasizing your views, you should stop emphasizing the end result of it, and start foreseeing how these things occur, not in terms of psychologizing and just explain to yourself how this happened,
[SPEAKER_00]: But the moments, the day when you are deciding to go against the sense restraint or distraction, you start emphasizing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as I said, you will have no immediate criteria that that's the right way to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're pressured on the level of the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're pressured to clarify the views, to resolve the views, to attain the views.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like, yeah, well, you gotta put that second and actually emphasize body, speech and mind, actions, routine, greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, okay, I've been emphasizing it, but what now?
[SPEAKER_00]: What now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is my view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you have to have faith and keep emphasizing the right order of things, the right development.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, your own pressure of where are my views and what's happening will subside.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it relates back to what you were just saying about that pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're trying to be sense-restrained, and then pressure builds up, and at some point you break the sense-restraint, and then, oh, damn, I broke it again.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, it can kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: I think that, oh, like, oh, because I acted out of it, therefore, this danger and problems that I thought I was understanding, must not be clear enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: I must think about it more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's completely, like, the wrong... Yeah, you can think about it more, but you need to realize that
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how much you kind of manage to sort of build up that inspirational kind of thinking, it will fade away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's natural.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things come and go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you still have to then recognize that you really need to start emphasizing that, the behavioral aspect of it, and things that you won't do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, the pressure will build up inevitably.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you realize, okay, I need to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you still have an option as to what you act out towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't need to be sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I need to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just too much pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I was careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: I still don't know to what extent and how.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, technically, it's acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not acting out on the level of fully distracting yourself with sense desires or winding yourself up with ill will and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those kind of neutral acting-outs, or not as unwholesome acting-outs, won't make you drift too far away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, then, you can recompose better.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all that... the simile in that sutra, it would have said, like, even if a monk, having gone to the forest, he's not making any effort, he's just sleeping all day, and having sensual thoughts all day long, and just not...
[SPEAKER_00]: Nevertheless, he's in a more suitable environment, his mind will eventually calm down and compose.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consequently, you have a monk in the middle of the village who is not sleeping, who is very diligent, who is not having lustful thoughts, but he's in the unsuitable environment with constant exposure to sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, so his mind will lose composure.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think there's also there's also just an aspect that, you know, it's not that I need to kind of clarify these things more so that there will be no pressure to act out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's so, like, the whole point is that
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, you have to start by not acting out in the face of everything that's... oh, I must... but I must... there is this pressure, but I don't act out of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, like, regardless of it... and that's how you would actually build up further clarity, and that would then make that pressure diminish in future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's going to the village or the city or as he's traveling around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's these gradual
[SPEAKER_01]: Distractions, gradual... Erosions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a cover-up, whereas in the forest it's kind of more of a... the opening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, things are a bit more apparent and clear to you as the person who's there alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind... Basically, forest is like a pool that doesn't have anywhere else to spill further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, on the base of the simile he read.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the forest, your pool of sensual thoughts can fill up, and pressures and so on, but there is nothing further external that can keep spilling further, and can cause more proliferation, and more distraction, and more density.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it remains in the environment the kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not suitable for that growth.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you remain in that environment, even if the mind is careless, sleepy, it's on, lazy, sensual, it will come down, because the environment just has nowhere else to spill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and it's easier to ignore those little faults, when there's lots going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you know, it's maybe...
[SPEAKER_01]: Being alone or isolated, to a certain degree, you are... your thoughts are clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you kind of... those things that you are thinking, doing, are clearer to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, to some... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, now that can become also...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll never see any person ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to recognize, no, it's all on the basis of where my intentions are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm finding the environment that can support, like, keeping the clarity in regard to my own choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: These little choices that would then result in building up these bigger pressures that then I would not be able to help myself and then act out of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like the clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not clear what you're doing, these little things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not clear about the little things that you're doing, where they're leading to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were clear... Well, why are you not clear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would a person not be clear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that because they haven't read enough suttas, for example?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're choosing at some... well...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you are clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you know, but you're choosing to ignore what you already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the reason for the lack of clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, I'm not clear because I just don't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Deep down, you know exactly what not to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially, like, you know, you read a few suttas, have listened to some talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more than enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: To paint a clear picture of what should be done and what shouldn't be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, the lack of clarity builds up, but not because you simply don't know what you're doing, but because on that smaller, subtler scale, you're actually going against the clarity that you know you already have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you know you shouldn't do, you're doing it and you're ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that builds up, and then it comes to the point of what you obviously know you shouldn't do, means nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still do it, because you built it up so far.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pools have filled up, so now you can just magically unplug it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, someone's doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the habit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of restraining and then gradually...
[SPEAKER_01]: Slipping.
[SPEAKER_01]: Concealing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing that you're doing something wrong, but... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowingly, kind of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the habit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the habit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the first step to break out of that habit?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's... what will throw a spanner in that... in that kind of thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would throw a spanner in that kind of thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I know, yeah, it is... it's clear to me that...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's clear that it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel ashamed afterwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know you shouldn't have done it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you don't do it for a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the carelessness, the distraction, the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Builds up the lack of clarity and then you do it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, same cycle.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the first step to break that cycle?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the the growth in the discipline of a noble one?
[SPEAKER_03]: Recognizing a mistake... an offense as an offense, or... Well, recognizing is not enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: This person recognizes it every time, but then slips away and the recognition drifts away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the... what's the act that's... that's... that's the spanner in the works?
[SPEAKER_03]: Revealing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bringing it out to the light, confessing it to somebody else, so you feel that shame,
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel that weight, you feel that disgust even, but it's out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't hide it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That last layer of, oh well, this is just in here, it's gone now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a way of addressing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like any addiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people who are addicts, you know, with drugs and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to admit, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have to first, they have to say it, but it doesn't just help saying it internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I know, heroin is wrong, and now they give it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: They always have to ask or speak to others, say it out loud in a group, keep repeating it to themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm an alcoholic, my name is such and such.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's also... it helps with, like, you know, you might sort of feel to some... you might feel ashamed of yourself when you do these things, but if you really say it to somebody else, it's like, you know, it's kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's out of your hands.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It really forces you to... well, forces, but it helps to take up responsibility for it as well, because now, okay, it's not only me who knows about this, other people do as well, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's like one thing, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: As monastics, we would have that, you know, that's the protocol, you know, you break a rule, you confess it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as a, like a lay person, just keeping the five precepts, eight precepts by themselves outside, that can be a big obstacle, I reckon, you know, because who do you confess to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yourself, well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but no, if somebody wants to, wants to train their mind and
[SPEAKER_00]: Knows right is right and wrong is wrong and what they shouldn't be doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, they keep losing the context, going back to it, building up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You say, you say it publicly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, eh... to a group, to a monk, to two monks, to five monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just because it's like, yeah, this is who I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not gonna feel pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that can be more than enough to, to bring you back into shape.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like it's the growth in the practice.